ILGWU Local 22 Education Department Records 5780/057
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Local 22 Education Department Records
1930-1979
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU). Local 22
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU)
5780/057
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Clippings, correspondence, newsletters, photographs, speeches.
The records of the Education Department of Local 22 consist of correspondence, newspaper clippings, newsletters, programs, photographs, and speeches documenting the activities of the Department from the 1930s to the 1970s. In addition to documentating the Department's activities, there is material on the local's political involvement with the Liberal Party of New York State and some items about aid to the Republican cause during the Spanish Civil War. There are also some materials dealing with international labor cooperation, civil rights, and communism in the U.S. Correspondents include Joseph Mazur and Saby Nehama.
3654767
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, October 07, 2008
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, June 13, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
The Education Department of Local 22 was developed to further the educational and cultural development of the Local's membership. It routinely sponsored lectures and courses on a variety of labor and other topics; it also offered musical and dramatic performances on a regular basis, either for or featuring its membership.
Local 22 of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU), also known as the Dressmakers' Union, was chartered in December 1920 and based in New York City. The dress industry formed its own Joint Board in 1921 composed of Local 22 Dressmakers, Local 25 Waistmakers, Local 58 Waist Buttonhole Makers, Local 60 Waist and Dress Pressers, Local 66 Bonnaz Embroidery Workers, Local 89 Italian Waist and Dressmakers, and the waist and dress branch of Cutters' Local 10. A general work stoppage in February 1923 in the dress industry won the union a 40 hour week and 10 percent wage increase, as well as a large gain of new members. During the summer of 1923, after years of discussion and deliberation, the two dress locals, Local 23 and 22 were consolidated. The dressmakers from Local 23 transferred to Local 22 and subsequently Local 22 joined the New York Cloakmakers' Joint Board. Soon, the Dress and Waist Joint Board became unnecessary and was dissolved. Local 25 Waistmakers were left without an affiliated organization and in October 1924 merged with the Dressmakers' Union, Local 22.
By the end of 1926, the Communists had gained control of the dress organization in New York City and the union barely existed. In February 4, 1930, 25,000 dressmakers walked out of the shops. The strike was called to reorganize dressmakers and finally abolish the Communist influence in the industry. On April 8, 1930 the General Executive Board decided to separate the dressmakers from the Cloakmakers' Joint Board. In 1931, Charles Zimmerman formed a committee to rebuild Local 22. He was elected to executive board of Local 22 in 1932, and elected manager-secretary in 1933. Another walkout in all dress shops, both union and non-union on August 16, 1933 brought the dress industry to a halt.
Zimmerman left Local 22 in 1958 to become manager of the Dress Joint Board. Israel Breslow succeeded him as manager of Local 22 from 1958 until his retirement in 1975. By 1975, the New York Dress Joint Board completed restructuring of affiliate locals, and Locals 60-60A, 159, and 38 were merged into existing Locals 22 and 89. Local 22 gained jurisdiction over all dressmakers in Manhattan. In the 1980s, more locals were dissolved and members transferred to Local 22, but by 1984, Local 22 saw restructuring as well. Changes in the garment industry necessitated the dissolution of the Joint Board and Local 22 into the new Local 89-22-1.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Education Department of Local 22 are made up of correspondence, newspaper clippings, newsletters, programs, photographs and speeches documenting the activities of the department from the 1930s to the 1970s. The newsletters, pamphlets and brochures detail the multitude of events and activities organized by the Education Department. The calendars in the collection show with daily listings, and illustrate the wide range of offerings with recreation such as concerts and gym classes, tap dancing and art workshops, and education with classes in English, citizenship, public speaking, trade unionism, social labor and legislation.
The Education Department held dances and festivals, often specific to the many ethnic groups in the union, and organized excursions such as boat cruises, outings to Unity House, trips to Puerto Rico, and a tour of Spain, North Africa and Portugal. There are also records of Club 22, which was comprised of the women members of Local 22. Club 22 planned activities such as dances and holiday parties, and brought in speakers and held lectures. The collection contains programs, fliers and correspondence detailing the events put on by the club for each calendar year.
Within the local there was the Dressmakers Liberal Party Club formed in reaction to the passage of the Taft-Hartley bill to organize dressmakers for effective action on the political field. The group held meetings to discuss campaigns, candidates, and current politics that could affect dressmakers, and the records include membership lists, correspondence, and information about meetings.
The second series of the collection contains the correspondence of Saby Nehama. Nehama was the secretary of the Dressmakers Liberal Party, a Business Agent for Local 22, and worked in the Education Department.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780/014: ILGWU Local 22, Charles S. Zimmerman Papers 5780/014 P: ILGWU Local 22, Charles S. Zimmerman Photographs 5780/015: ILGWU Local 22 Records 5780/036: ILGWU Local 22 Minutes 5780/057 P: ILGWU Local 22 Education Department Photographs 5780/067: ILGWU Local 22 Israel Breslow Papers
Arrangement
Series I: Subject Files, 1930-1973
Series II: Saby Nehama Correspondence, 1949-1969
Civil rights--United States.; Communism--United States.; International labor activities.; Labor unions and education--New York (State)--New York.; Working class--Education--New York (State)--New York.; New York (State)--Politics and government--1865-1950.; New York (State)--Politics and government--1951- .; Spain--History-- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Mazur, Joseph.; Nehama, Saby.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 22 (New York, N.Y.).Education Dept.; Liberal Party of New York State.
3654767
- Series Series I: Subject Files, 1930-1973
  - Civil Rights, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Robert Kennedy letter w. enclosed report on the progress in the field of civil rights.
  - Club 22, 1948-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Announcements, programs, printed material and related correspondence.
  - Club 22, 1958-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Club 22, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes undated material.
  - Communism, U.S.A., 1946-1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Contributions, 1948-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Convention, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Newspaper clippings.
  - The Dressmaker, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Economic Cooperation Administration, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Incl. text of conversation between James B. Carey (CIO) and Giuseppe Di Vittorio (Italian Confederation of Labor).
  - Education Department, 1933-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Announcements and programs.
  - Education Department. Live and Let Learn. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Local newsletter.
  - Education Department, 1961-1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Report 1962. Financial data, 1961,1971.
  - Entertainment, 1936-1957 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Excursions, Outings, Trips. [folder 1 of 4], 1949-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Excursions, Outings, Trips. [folder 2 of 4], 1949-1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Excursions, Outings, Trips. [folder 3 of 4], 1949-1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Excursions, Outings, Trips. [folder 4 of 4], 1949-1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Excursions, Outings, Trips, 1950-1966 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Wilson Line Contracts.
  - Is Economy Wealth? The Dressmakers' Struggle With the I.L.G.W.U. (1920's) by Grace Palladino., 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Thesis for B.A. Mount Holyoke College, South Hadley, Mass. 1975, 116 pp.
  - Lena's Boy a play in three acts by Luby Miller, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Politics, 1952-1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    General.
  - Politics. Dressmakers Liberal Party Club. [folder 1 of 2], 1947-1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Call to meetings.
  - Politics. Dressmakers Liberal Party Club. [folder 2 of 2], 1947-1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Politics. Dressmakers Liberal Party Club., 1961-1970 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    District lists
  - Politics. Dressmakers Liberal Party Club., 1951-1963 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Membership lists
  - Politics. Dressmakers Liberal Party Club and Liberal Party material, 1948-1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Politics. Liberal Party (and Dressmakers Liberal Party Club), 1965-1974 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Resolutions, 1934-1959 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Seminar (Local 22), 1964 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Croton-on-Hudson. June 1964.
  - Spain, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Trade Union Relief for Spain.
  - Spanish Dressmakers (Local 22), 1930 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Incl. Left-wing material during the 1930's.
  - Speeches, 1950-1959 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Taft-Hartley Act, 1949-1957 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series Series II: Saby Nehama Correspondence, 1949-1969
  - Bartoli, Jose (artist in Mexico), 1949-1968 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Calera, Marie (business agent), 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    9/1/54-7/3/57. Correspondence during leave of absence in Spain & Mexico.
  - Inter-American Federation of Textile Garment and Leather Workers Union, 1962-1969 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Corres. w. trade unions in Central & South America.
  - Spain, 1937-1952 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Letters from Spanish Republican militiamen who came to U.S. for aid. Subsequent letters from these visitors.
  - United States Department of Labor, Bureau of Internal Affairs, 1955-1968 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Images digitized from the collection. (Box 5)
- Text digitized from the collection. (Box 6)